[{"topic": "Education", "question": "In this position you may be working with individuals who are underage and/or vulnerable. We do full background checks on all of our employees. Are you willing to comply?", "answers": ["This is where you must disclose to the interviewer if you do not have a clean criminal background. Discuss with the interviewer your willingness to comply and be sure to disclose any pain points ahead of time. It is better they find any marks on your record directly from you! \n\nIf you have a clean criminal background: \"Yes, I am happy to comply with any criminal, financial, and educational related background checks that you require. My record is clean.\"", "\"Yes, I am happy to comply with any criminal, financial, and educational related background checks that you require. My record is clean.\"", "If you do not have a clean criminal background: \"I am happy to comply with any criminal, financial, and educational related background check that you require. The majority will come back clean; however, I should disclose to you that I have a DUI charge from 7 years ago that may come up. I have been cleared of charges now and my drivers' license has been reinstated.\""]}, {"topic": "Education", "question": "In our industry, your day may not be a typical 8AM - 4PM. Are you willing to work overtime and participate in extra-curricular activities?", "answers": ["The education industry is often in demand, even outside of typical school hours and activities. If you have restrictions in your schedule, this is a great time to address those restrictions.\n\nIf you have an open schedule: \"I am available to work most of the time, with some notice on overtime if possible.\"", "\"I am available to work most of the time, with some notice on overtime if possible.\"", "If you have scheduling restrictions: \"I do take an evening course every Thursday so I would not be available for additional hours those days. Other than that, I am happy to make myself available as often as possible.\""]}, {"topic": "Education", "question": "Do you think honesty is always the best policy?", "answers": ["Is honesty always the best policy? Talk to the interviewer about your thoughts on honesty in the workplace.", "\"Sometimes full disclosure can damage someone's self esteem, and reality isn't always best expressed in full and can be self-indulgent based on the person's intention. In those instances, honesty isn't always the best policy.\"", "\"Honesty is always the best policy.  Often times, it is just a matter of how you communicate and deliver your message so managing this with each situation is critical to building honest and trustworthy relationships.\""]}, {"topic": "Education", "question": "Do you prefer working with a student one-on-one or with a larger class of students?", "answers": ["Discuss you preference with the interviewer and be sure to highlight your overall experience; whether that be with larger classes of students or one-on-one. You can keep your answer brief and be sure to avoid talking yourself out of a job. (IE: if this is a tutoring company, avoid discussing how you do not enjoy one-on-one student interaction.)", "\"As an educator for the past 4 years I feel that I have developed a strong ability to adapt to nearly every teaching situation. I do not lean strongly to group settings versus individual settings; however, I always enjoy seeing how students interact with each other when a challenge is at hand.\"", "\"I  tend to enjoy teaching larger groups at a time simply because of the energy a class full of students can offer. Also, the insightful questions that can come from a solid group session are pretty surprising at times. With that said, at times it is easier to make a direct impact when you teach one-on-one. I am satisfied with either method.\""]}, {"topic": "Education", "question": "At Company ABC we seek to hire those who are passionate about education. How would you describe your teaching/mentorship style?", "answers": ["If you have ever heard of an \"Elevator Pitch\" - this type of interview question is a great reason to have one! Why do you love what you do? What makes you the best, and most engaged, potential hire for Company ABC? Briefly discuss your teaching and mentorship style and close by giving an example of a time when you were recognized for your teaching or leadership methods.", "Here are some keys to effective mentorship that you can draw on, for your response: \n\n- Committed \n- Collaborative \n- Encouraging\n- Willing to pass on knowledge \n- Approachable \n- Patient\n- Honest\n- Diplomatic\n- Ability to give constructive feedback \n- Continued learner \n- Curious \n- Objective \n- Genuine"]}, {"topic": "Education", "question": "How do you define success?", "answers": ["What does success mean to you? Tell the interviewer how you see success and be sure to tie your answer into the success that you plan to bring to this particular position, should you be offered the role.", "\"I define success by my ability to reach the goals that are set out for me. On a personal level, the things I wish to achieve in my life. On a work level, the targets that are set out for me as well as the professional development that I seek.\"", "\"I define success by what we achieve as a team. The faculty, as a whole, needs to deliver on expectations before I consider anything a success.\""]}, {"topic": "Education", "question": "Do you always double check or proofread your work?", "answers": ["Double checking and proofreading are a very important parts of a job well done. Assure the interviewer that you are diligent when it comes to submitting good, clean, work.", "\"Spelling and grammatical errors are a pet peeve of mine. I will triple check my work if there is time! I feel that it is very important to submit error free work.\"", "\"I am so accustomed to working under pressure and tight deadlines that I do forget to double check my work at times. This is a habit that I have consciously been working on to improve.\""]}, {"topic": "Education", "question": "What are your thoughts on public vs. private education?", "answers": ["The topic of public vs. private education is a hot one! When you are asked to discuss a controversial topic in an interview it is best to avoid any offending statements or pushing any buttons. Give a rather cooled opinion on both sides and leave it at that.", "\"I can understand why some people would want their children in private school as much as I understand the draw of public school. Not everyone can afford the luxury of private school but I am thankful that our public school system offers a great education with such little cost associated. In my opinion, as long as our kids are receiving a valuable education then who am I to say whether one is better than the other.\"", "\"I primarily stand behind public education because it is affordable for everyone, and it provides educational access to anyone regardless of their social standing. Many times, the classrooms will be more manageable in size, and these classrooms are more likely to offer a more diverse range of students. With that said, I do understand why some parents prefer private education for their children. Perhaps its a family tradition or they prefer the coursework and other opportunities that come along with a private facility.\""]}, {"topic": "Education", "question": "Why do you want this job with Company ABC?", "answers": ["If you are lucky enough to land an interview, make some effort and conduct research on the opportunity. Think about how this job will help you in your career. It's important for you to know not only what you have to offer them, but what they can do for you. \n\nWhile your passion and excitement about the job are important, it's always good to have some hard facts to back it up. For instance, saying 'I have heard great things about your institution and I know I would be a great fit for this job', is not very specific.", "\"I am excited about this opportunity because your values are very much in line with mine. I deeply care about giving back to the community through educating our at-risk youth.\"", "\"I have had my eye on new openings in your school for some time now. Your reputation for employee development and community involvement is something that I admire. I see a long term fit here.\""]}, {"topic": "Education", "question": "At Company ABC we put a strong emphasis on continued education. We believe that there is always more to learn. How do you feel about continued education?", "answers": ["Of course education is important when you are working in the education industry! Assure the interviewer that you are not resistant to continued education. Perhaps there is a course, program, or workshop that you are personally interested in? Discuss with the interviewer your passion for education.", "\"I wholeheartedly agree that education is incredibly important. We can always learn more! Personally, I like to take a short course or workshop 3-4 times per year. These courses have included additional computer, leadership, and mentorship related training.\"", "\"Continued education is imperative to my growth as an education professional. I feel strongly about continuing to grow my knowledge in this industry. Could you give me some examples of the ways that Company ABC emphasizes continued education in its employees?\""]}, {"topic": "Education", "question": "Private and franchised adult learning institutions have greatly increased in popularity over the years. Do you see value in these institutions? Why or why not?", "answers": ["The topic of franchised adult learning institutions can be a controversial one! When you are asked to discuss a controversial topic in an interview it is best to avoid any offending statements or pushing any buttons. Give a rather cooled opinion on both sides and leave it at that.", "\"I can understand the draw when it comes to franchised adult learning institutions. Not everyone can attend University right out of High School and many have the option to return to school later on in life.  In my opinion, continued Education is important. As long as the courses being offered are legitimate ones, who am I to stand in the way?\"", "\"I primarily support traditional learning that comes from a University or long-standing College. I feel that the coursework is more likely to be recognized. I would not like to see someone complete a diploma at a franchised institution just to later find out that their courses are not recognized. If they can guarantee course credit recognition, then that is great.\""]}, {"topic": "Education", "question": "Take a few minutes to walk me through your post-secondary education.", "answers": ["Your post-secondary education is likely listed on your resume; however, this is an opportunity to talk to the interviewer about your overall experience. Discuss any accolades and special recognition you may have received. You can also discuss a class or a project that impacted you the most during that time.", "\"I graduated with a Bachelor's of Outdoor Leadership and Education from Toccoa Falls College in 2006. My experience in that program was great! Even though I worked part time, I was still able to make the Dean's list, received a partial scholarship and graduated top of my class.\"", "\"In 2009 I completed my Bachelor's of Education and immediately followed that with a Masters' Degree in English. I am very proud of my educational background and am happy with the opportunities that this level of education has allowed me. I would love to continue this education down the road to include a Doctorate.\""]}, {"topic": "Education", "question": "Tell me about your greatest work related accomplishment.", "answers": ["Talking about your greatest accomplishment will give the interviewer a strong idea of where you place your values. It will also show the interviewer more about your personality, how you like to be motivated, and how to coach you in the future. It is okay to brag a little bit when answering this question. Show that you are proud of yourself and your career accomplishments!", "\"The greatest accomplishment in my career was graduating University as an honors student while still working full time in a related field. I was top of my class, and working full time. This showed me that I am able to dedicate myself to my career, and reach the goals that I set for myself. It felt great to accomplish so much and be recognized for my dedication.\"", "\"I have many accomplishments that I am very proud of. Overall, I would say that my greatest work accomplishment is the positive reputation that I have as an educator. Reputation is everything and I am proud of mine.\""]}, {"topic": "Education", "question": "How do you like to encourage ideas in others?", "answers": ["Encouragement to others is a great skill to possess. Talk to the interviewer about your ability to encourage creative ideas in your team members.", "\"I like to encourage other people to be creative in their thinking and present ideas to their classrooms, no matter how off the wall they may seem. Some of our most successful teachers are ones who are confident in their ability to bring forward their unique ideas. I encourage participation through an open door policy and strong praise for those who show initiative.\"", "\"I encourage people to tap into the best parts of themselves. It helps to ask probing questions to get them to generate ideas on their own. If you paint a long term vision for where you want to go towards, you will be surprised at the creative solutions your team will come up with to get you there.\""]}, {"topic": "Education", "question": "Tell me about a teacher, leader, or mentor who affected your life in a positive way.", "answers": ["When you work in the Education industry it is important to understand the difference that a strong leader and mentor can make in the life of a student. Talk to the interviewer briefly about someone who may have helped you along the way. Does anyone influential come to mind?", "\"In my elementary years I had some trouble with reading. My grade 2 teacher was a very patient and kind person who went above her duties by giving me additional resources. Because she was generous with her time and efforts, I was exceeding grade level expectations in no time. In addition to catching up academically, I was able to gain a lot of personal confidence.\"", "\"I believe that every teacher and leader that I have had has played their own part in positively affecting my life. From a young age I have been lucky enough to have excellent mentors who wanted to invest in my future. It's a large part of why I wanted to work in the field of education, myself.\""]}, {"topic": "Education", "question": "At Company ABC, we seek to hire the most compassionate individuals. Do you consider yourself compassionate?", "answers": ["The best way to answer a question like this is to give a clear and concise example of how you consistently show your compassionate character. Do you help students in your free time? Perhaps you volunteer? Have you received recognition for your efforts from a previous employer? Brainstorm some examples  that show off your great character!", "\"I was raised to be a compassionate person and do consider myself to possess this quality. One way that I show this is by volunteering my time as an after-school tutor for kids who are struggling in school and who lack the resources at home. I have been committed to this volunteer work for the past 2 years.\"", "\"I believe compassion is a must-have trait for anyone wishing to succeed in the field of education. When I think of compassion, I think of the quote from Arthur Schopenhauer that says, \"Compassion is the basis of morality.\" I truly believe in this and try to practice it every day.\""]}, {"topic": "Education", "question": "If you could be a subject matter expert in any subject of your choice, which would you choose?", "answers": ["Talk to the interviewer about the topics that pique your interest the most. If you could immerse yourself in a particular subject, what would it be and why? You can make your answer a bit lighthearted and personal if you wish.", "\"Ever since I was a child I have been fascinated with mechanics and design. I would build models of airplanes and cars in my room for hours at a time. I still have a very keen interest in design so I would say that if I could be a subject matter expert on any topic - I would choose mechanical engineering.\"", "\"That's a great question! In my spare time I do a lot of reading on socioeconomic related matters. I would love to be seen as a subject matter expert in how the effects of race and social standing directly impact career choice variables. It's all very fascinating to me.\""]}, {"topic": "Education", "question": "Tell me about an organization or group outside of work that you contributed to.", "answers": ["Many hiring managers will choose one candidate over another because of their volunteer experience. They feel that it shows strong character and selflessness...all qualities that make a great employee. Talk to the interviewer about your willingness to give back to your community in some form of volunteerism. If you do not have formal volunteer experience you can draw on things you do in your spare time to assist friends, family, or even your current employer. \n\nIf you do have volunteer experience: \"For the past 8 months I have volunteered every Wednesday evening at our local animal shelter. I will help with grooming the animals, feeding them, and walking them. It's been a really fun experience and rewarding at the same time.\"", "\"For the past 8 months I have volunteered every Wednesday evening at our local animal shelter. I will help with grooming the animals, feeding them, and walking them. It's been a really fun experience and rewarding at the same time.\"", "If you do not have volunteer experience: \"I have not formally volunteered in these most recent years, however; I spend a lot of time helping my sister who is a single mom. I will babysit on weekends, cook dinners for her and drive the kids to appointments when necessary. I feel that it is very important to take care of the needs of family.\""]}, {"topic": "Education", "question": "When have you had to adapt to change?", "answers": ["Being able to adapt to change in the workplace is a very important skill to possess. Talk to the interviewer about a time when you have had to adjust to changes on the job. How did you handle the change? Was it a positive reaction?", "\"I feel that educators adapt to change on a daily basis! The vibe in the classroom is different every day, student moods and efforts vary as well. I am well accustomed to working in a changing environment.\"", "\"After being a dedicated mathematics teacher for the past 10 years, I was asked to take on a new focus this coming year. I am currently prepping myself to teach chemistry as well. It's been a challenge but I am actually really excited for the change.\""]}, {"topic": "Education", "question": "If you could start your career over again, what direction would you take?", "answers": ["A hiring manager will be able to tell a lot about your personality by learning about your other career interests. If you could do anything over, what would you do, and why?", "\"I certainly do not regret the direction I have taken my career; however, if I had to completely start over in a new direction I would likely pursue a degree in Mechanical Engineering and become an Engineer. Both of my parents were Engineers and they seemed to have a very fulfilling career. I enjoy analytics and research which I tend to do a lot of in my role as an educator.\"", "\"I am very satisfied with the direction my career has taken. If I could change anything I would perhaps have furthered my education to include a Masters' degree.\""]}, {"topic": "Education", "question": "When entering a new job, describe how you build relationships with your new coworkers and supervisors.", "answers": ["Due to a wide variety of personalities, relationships can take time to form. How do you ensure that you have a strong line of communication with your co-workers and supervisors, right from the start?", "\"I understand that some relationships come quickly and others take time to nurture. When starting a new job all that I can do is be my true self and let my personality, integrity, and reliability speak for itself.\"", "\"I get along well with most personalities. My colleagues were great team players and we would often meet up after work for drinks or team activities. I would simply start there, when starting a new job. Becoming involved in post-work activities and continuing to be the social person that I am.\""]}, {"topic": "Education", "question": "How do you believe you will complement our department, if you were hired?", "answers": ["If you were awarded the position, what would you bring to the department or organization? Assure the interviewer that you are the right fit for this position.", "\"If I were hired, I feel that I would compliment your faculty in a few significant ways. First - I am a fast learner and I already bring 6 years' experience in the education industry. The time to train me will be reduced. Also, I will bring a very strong curriculum with me which will make an impact almost immediately.\"", "\"If I were hired, I will compliment your department by adding value to the pressing initiatives you have prioritized.  I am excited to share my knowledge when it comes to cross-departmental efforts.\""]}, {"topic": "Education", "question": "Give an example of when you used your listening skills to solve a problem.", "answers": ["The interviewer wants to see that you have strong listening skills. They want to see that you aren't the type to interrupt before hearing your co-workers out. When it comes to using your listening skills while receiving direction from your employer, asking for clarification can save you a lot of grief down the road! Show that you are one to check for full understanding when you are navigating new territory. Highlight to the interviewer that you are the type to attentively listen and troubleshoot problems in a collaborative style.  \n\nSomeone with good listening skills will: \n\n- Give the speaker their full attention \n- Maintain proper eye contact\n- Show invested interest by nodding or agreeing \n- Avoid interrupting\n- Ask for clarification if needed \n- Make statements such as \"If I am understanding you correctly...\" or \"Do you mean that you want...\"\n\nGive an example that demonstrates how you avoided miscommunication by using your stellar listening skills!", "\"My current principal is very brief in her communication and sometimes it creates confusion within the faculty. Last month she asked me to run a report on a student whose parents she was meeting with the next day. I wasn't entirely sure that I understood what she was asking.  After she finished telling me what she was looking for, I repeated it back to her. I will often use qualifying questions such as, 'So what you're asking is...?' or 'Do you mean that you want me to do (X)?' This seems to avoid a lot of unnecessary problems down the road.\""]}, {"topic": "Education", "question": "List the top 3 skills that you have acquired in your last role.", "answers": ["You have likely gained many valuable skills in your career. Share with the interviewer which skills you value the most. Be sure to include skills that will benefit this potential new employer.", "\"In the past few years I was able to upgrade my education while still working full time. The biggest skill that I gained was my ability to multi-task as I worked the dual role of employee and student.\"", "\"My last role was very challenging and was a big step in my career. The top 3 skills that I acquired would be my student relationship skills, clear communication skills, and ability to prioritize.\""]}, {"topic": "Education", "question": "What leadership qualities do you possess?", "answers": ["Some great qualities of a leader are:\n\n- Being someone who people naturally want to follow\n- Exceptional interpersonal skills\n- Strong relationship building skills\n- Taking ownership for the team's errors and mistakes\n- Excelling at motivating others\n- Providing kudos to your team\n- Knowing how to select and hire the right people to join the team\n- Having a vision for the future\n\nThese are just a few to get started!  Which qualities do you most identify with?", "\"I possess great leadership qualities that include diligence, tenacity, and open communication. I look forward to taking these skills to work for you!\""]}, {"topic": "Education", "question": "What are your salary expectations?", "answers": ["The best way to discuss your salary expectations are to use your current earnings as an example. Be open, and honest. Transparency is the best choice when salary based questions arise.", "\"Currently, I earn a base salary of $45,000 per year plus a potential 20% annual bonus. Last year my earnings were $52,000 and I would like to stay in the same range or slightly higher.\"", "\"I am currently making $80,000 per year.  I am looking for compensation that is aligned with the role and provides opportunity for growth.\""]}, {"topic": "Education", "question": "How do you handle stress on the job?", "answers": ["Are you someone who is able to handle stress on the job? How do you manage the stressful times? Talk to the interviewer about your ability to manage pressure in the workplace.", "\"I handle stress very well and when you call my references, they will attest to this fact. When I am under pressure on the job, I focus on the task at hand and make sure to not get distracted. Staying on deadline is very helpful and I will delegate when necessary to alleviate some stress.\"", "\"Stress is part of any demanding job and I embrace it to the fullest.  I take good care of myself personally and prioritize my workload to maintain a healthy balance in my stress levels.\""]}, {"topic": "Education", "question": "Tell me something about yourself that I wouldn't know from reading your resume.", "answers": ["The interviewer would like to get to know you apart from what is written on your resume. You are certainly not obligated to discuss personal matters such as your kids, or relationship status, for instance. Stick with a couple of fun facts to show the interviewer that you are a real person, too. Your answer should be unique so that you are a memorable candidate!  \n\nFocus on special non-work related skills or hobbies.  For example, you might share that you enjoy beat-boxing or making origami swans. Be prepared for the interviewer to stop you and ask you to perform your skill on the spot when it's possible! (This will make you unforgettable!)", "\"I am an avid marathon runner and have traveled to 10 countries in the last 8 years to compete in a variety of races. I am a competitive individual and enjoy keeping fit.\"", "\"I am bilingual in Spanish and have some proficiency in French and Italian, too. I also am a huge Harry Potter fan and could pretty much quote each book to you!\""]}, {"topic": "Education", "question": "What questions do you have for me?", "answers": ["It's always a great idea to have questions ready for the interviewer. Review the company website and other online resources to ensure the questions you are asking are not mundane, or redundant. The last thing an interviewer wants to hear is a list of questions you could have found the answers to from a simple Google search. \n\nHere are some sample questions: \n\n- When would you like to have this position filled? \n- How long has this role been vacant? \n- Is this a replacement search or a newly created role? \n- What is your favorite part about working here? \n- What is the facility's primary goal for this position in the next 12 months? \n- Is there anything from my background and experience that I can clarify for you? \n- What do you see as the biggest change in this industry over the past 3 years? \n- Is there any reason why you would not hire me?", "\"Thank you for asking - I do have a few questions. What is top of mind when it comes to filling this role? In addition, what types of career growth opportunities would follow this position? And lastly, do you have internal candidates who are also interviewing for this position?\""]}, {"topic": "Nonprofit", "question": "At Company ABC we prefer to hire those who have a penchant for sales and fundraising. Have you ever had a fundraising target from a previous nonprofit employer?", "answers": ["Many people enter the nonprofit sector because they want to help people. What they do not realize is that nonprofit organizations also have funding needs to meet. Assure the interviewer that you will not shy away from aggressive fundraising targets.", "\"I have had multiple sales positions and have also owned my own business in the past. I fully understand that a nonprofit organization still has a bottom line. In my last position with ABC, I was tasked with raising $500K per quarter in charitable contributions.\"", "\"In my most recent position I have had multiple targets to reach; whether geared towards dollars, volunteer hours, or regular sponsorship's. I am always on top of my KPI's and targets, setting clear and achievable milestones for myself.\""]}, {"topic": "Nonprofit", "question": "What experience do you have using team-based messaging applications?", "answers": ["There are many options for communication software and messaging applications. Give the interviewer a brief overview of the apps you are experienced in and assure them that you can learn their internal system, should it be new to you.", "\"I have used a variety of team-based messaging applications. I am best versed in Brosix, AOL Instant Messenger, and Freedcamp. No matter which system you use I am sure that I can pick it up very quickly.\"", "\"I do not have a lot of experience with team-based messaging applications besides MSN Messenger years ago. I do pick up on technology quickly and have no concerns when it comes to my ability to learn. What team-based messaging applications do you use?\""]}, {"topic": "Nonprofit", "question": "Do you have experience in recruiting volunteers?", "answers": ["A large part of the success of a nonprofit organization comes from it's dedicated volunteers. A nonprofit organization will often have recruitment fairs to find and onboard more significant amounts of volunteers. Talk to the interviewer about any experience you have in attracting potential volunteers.", "\"In my current position I have recruited a total of 40 volunteers in the last year. I am very vocal about my love for volunteering and hope that it's contagious enough to attract others. I have also helped at hiring fairs for Company ABC. I am comfortable in interviewing and screening potential volunteers as well.\"", "\"I do not have experience in recruiting volunteers; however, this is a responsibility that I would enjoy learning more about. I am eager to expand my capabilities and feel I would be great in this capacity as I am thorough, with strong intuition.\""]}, {"topic": "Nonprofit", "question": "We want to know what you are passionate about. If you could work for any cause, what would you choose?", "answers": ["This question is a perfect time to show the interviewer a little bit about yourself and your passions. Don't hold back, but be sure to talk about how the cause at Company ABC is of interest to you as well.", "\"I am passionate about any cause to do with helping children and animals. One of my greatest passions is my volunteer work with the local humane society. I feel that working with Company ABC would help me to round out my passions. I'm very excited about this opportunity.\"", "\"There are so many worthy causes - that is a challenging question! I have a soft spot in my heart for the disabled. My sister has a physical disability, and I have worked very hard for many years to advocate for individuals with both physical and mental disabilities. If I could continue to advocate for this cause, for a living, that would be so fulfilling for me.\""]}, {"topic": "Nonprofit", "question": "Tell me about a time when you took the initiative to improve work related procedures.", "answers": ["Have you ever taken the opportunity to present your employer with potential change? Talk to the hiring manager about a time when you took the initiative in the workplace.", "\"I was able to present and implement one specific change in the office this past year. It was a recycling program that I felt was very important, even for our smaller office. We had significantly less waste after my initiative was implemented and I enjoyed seeing others take pride in helping our environment.\"", "\"In my current position, I noticed that our written procedures were not exactly how the employees were doing things.  I decided to interview the employees and compare it to the written procedures that management wanted to be used.  We were able to come to a compromise that met all of the safety and quality requirements of the company, but still worked a bit faster and easier for the staff.\""]}, {"topic": "Nonprofit", "question": "Would you say you are a better verbal or written communicator?", "answers": ["In which manner do you prefer to communicate - written or verbal? Discuss your preference with the interviewer and support your answer.", "\"I prefer verbal communication because I feel that with written communication, a lot can be misread due to lack of tone, fluctuation, expression and body language. I will always choose a face to face conversation whenever possible.\"", "\"I like to leverage both methods of communications when dealing in business. Sometimes, situations call for verbal communications and other times, written.  As a rule of thumb, I tend to practice verbal communications, with written follow up or visa versa.  Utilizing multiple methods creates repetition and therefore, change.\""]}, {"topic": "Nonprofit", "question": "At Company ABC we want to work with individuals who value volunteerism. Walk me through your volunteer experience.", "answers": ["When applying for a nonprofit position you should be prepared to talk about how you give back to others, and how you contribute to your community. Show the interviewer that you can 'walk the walk.'", "\"I have been involved in volunteer work with our local community for the past ten years. I have worked at our local food bank, women's shelter and humane society.\"", "\"I am an avid volunteer at the local animal shelter and have been for the last five years. Animal care is critical to me which is why I am also a foster parent to animals who need to be re-homed but are having a tough time being placed. I believe that all living creatures should be loved and well cared for.\""]}, {"topic": "Nonprofit", "question": "Do you know anyone who has worked for Company ABC before? What kind of feedback have you received on our organization?", "answers": ["Have you ever discussed the workplace culture of Company ABC with a former or current employee? What have you heard in regards to the pros and cons of working here? Make sure to keep your answer positive.", "\"I have an acquaintance who has worked for Company ABC for a few years now. He has great things to say about the workplace culture. From what I understand, it's a very collaborative and creative environment here.\"", "\"I am not familiar with anyone within Company ABC; however, I have read a multitude of phenomenal reviews on Yelp, Google, and Glassdoor. The feedback has had a common theme of being well organized, treating your staff with respect, and offering transparency that is not always common in the nonprofit industry.\""]}, {"topic": "Nonprofit", "question": "Tell me about your greatest work related accomplishment.", "answers": ["Talking about your most significant accomplishment will give the interviewer a firm idea of where you place your values. It will also show the interviewer more about your personality, how you like to be motivated, and how to coach you in the future. It is okay to brag a little bit when answering this question. Show that you are proud of yourself and your career accomplishments!", "\"The greatest accomplishment in my career was graduating University as an honors student while still working full time in a related field. I was top of my class, and working full time. This accomplishment showed me that I could dedicate myself to my career, and reach the goals that I set for myself. It felt great to accomplish so much and be recognized for my dedication.\"", "\"I have many accomplishments of which I am very proud. Overall, I would say that my greatest work accomplishment is the positive reputation that I have in this industry.\""]}, {"topic": "Nonprofit", "question": "How do you prioritize multiple projects when they all seem equally important?", "answers": ["Prioritizing is a skill that requires practice. There are many approaches you can take. Here are some suggestions:\n\n1) Make a list. By thinking through and writing down each item that needs to be completed, you can see it on paper.\n2) Mark what is urgent or essential. Take into account deadlines and meetings.\n3) Order each task based on effort and estimated value. Considering due dates and how long it will take to do each item (also considering how much time you have). \n\nIn answering this question, show the interviewer that you have a system in place that helps you to think through what needs to happen, and when. The better you can prioritize, the more productive you will be, making you an asset to their company!", "\"I love to keep running lists of everything that I need to do, big or small. Mostly because I love crossing things off of the to-do list, but also because it helps me keep track of everything. Lately, I've started utilizing a free project management software that I use to make those lists, categorize the tasks, and mark them as a priority.\""]}, {"topic": "Nonprofit", "question": "How do you handle stress on the job?", "answers": ["Are you someone who can handle stress on the job? How do you manage the stressful times? Talk to the interviewer about your ability to control pressure in the workplace.", "\"I handle stress very well, and when you call my references, they will attest to this fact. When I am under pressure on the job, I focus on the task at hand and make sure not to get distracted. Staying on deadline is very helpful, and I will delegate when necessary to alleviate some stress.\"", "\"Stress is part of any demanding job, and I embrace it to the fullest.  I take good care of myself and prioritize my workload to maintain a healthy balance in my stress levels.\""]}, {"topic": "Nonprofit", "question": "How often do you take work home with you?", "answers": ["The majority of people will work overtime hours or take work home with them on occasion. Talk to the interviewer about how frequently to take your work home.", "\"I make sure to utilize my work hours very efficiently, so the only time that I take my work home is when there is an extremely stringent deadline. I would say that, overall, I take my work home maybe twice per month. It's all about being diligent with your time in the office!\"", "\"I value a strong balance between work and home life so I will only bring work home with me when I am at risk of missing a deadline or when there is an urgent need.\""]}, {"topic": "Nonprofit", "question": "How do you encourage generosity in others; whether that be their ability to contribute financially, or with their time?", "answers": ["The interviewer would like to know that you can be an active employee when it comes to fundraising and recruiting for Company ABC Talk to the interviewer about your ability to ask for donations, close a deal, or gain a commitment of time from volunteers.", "\"I spent a few years in a business development role before starting my career in nonprofit fund development. I am well connected and persuasive when it comes to gaining financial and time commitments from others.\"", "\"I believe that people will readily contribute financially, or with their time, when the cause is close to them or when they fully understand the impact that their contribution will make. I am open to individuals by showing them the impact they can make. This approach generally solicits very positive results.\""]}, {"topic": "Nonprofit", "question": "Why do you want to work in the nonprofit sector when you can earn more money working in a profit driven corporate environment?", "answers": ["Many nonprofit organizations cannot afford to pay the big salaries of profit-driven organizations. The interviewer wants to know that you are going to be okay with potentially earning less than the average person in your field. Talk to the interviewer about the other ways you will find satisfaction in this role.", "\"Compensation is always a factor; however, it is not the primary driving force behind my search. I am seeking an organization with a cause where I can make a difference.\"", "\"Working in nonprofit has always been my driving force, far above the concern of compensation. Of course, it is nice to earn a good living at the same time. What I value most is the idea of being pleased with my work, at the end of each day.\""]}, {"topic": "Nonprofit", "question": "At Company ABC we aim to hire individuals who can wear many different 'hats' in our organization. What other job functions could you perform?", "answers": ["Every nonprofit organization seeks to hire the most diverse talent possible. This strategy saves the cost of over-staffing and creating a strain on the budget if funds are low. Talk to the interviewer about your multiple skills and abilities. Now is not the time to be humble!", "\"I am competent in sales as well as online marketing and cold calling. I am very comfortable leading events and am also experienced in recruiting large amounts of volunteers.\"", "\"I have many transferable skills which include project management, employee training, interviewing, and succession planning.\""]}, {"topic": "Nonprofit", "question": "At Company ABC we want to hire those who are passionate about our cause. What do you know about our organization and how does our mission fit you?", "answers": ["Show the interviewer that you are fully engaged in this process by revealing the research you have conducted on Company ABC before the interview. How does their mission align with your values?", "\"I have always been passionate about XYZ which is why I have had an eye on openings within Company ABC for quite some time. Your mission is incredibly important, and I would be so proud to join you in that mission.\"", "\"I understand that your organization's primary focus is on (specify cause) and that your biggest project to date was the (name of the campaign). I appreciate the hard work and effort that went into this campaign, and I am very excited to work with such a well organized and well-branded organization.\""]}, {"topic": "Nonprofit", "question": "In your opinion, how does social media marketing fit with nonprofit fundraising?", "answers": ["More nonprofit organizations are seeing the benefits of social media for fundraising. Talk to the interviewer about your thoughts on this form of marketing. If you have ever taken on social media related activities, be sure to mention this to the interviewer.", "\"I was the social media marketing lead for Company ABC for approximately eight months while we back-filled a marketing position. I feel that small and fast fundraising goals work well on social media. The efforts don't necessarily need to be solely financial focused either. For instance, if you look at the ALS Ice Bucket Challenge. Not only did it raise an incredible amount of funds - but it also raised a huge amount of awareness of the disease.\"", "\"It's interesting that you ask this question, as I just read an article related to this the other day. One of the ways that social media marketing is beneficial to non-profits is because it allows continual engagement of its stakeholders. Another way social media is great is that it allows for global reach that one normally could not achieve.\""]}, {"topic": "Nonprofit", "question": "In your opinion, what are the greatest needs in our community?", "answers": ["Have an open discussion with the interviewer on what you feel are the most significant needs in your community at this time. Let your passion shine through! Avoid being negative or having a \"doomsday\" attitude. Remain positive and hopeful by talking about what you can do to make a difference.", "\"We have many needs in this large and diverse community. My initial instinct is that we need a focus on continued adult education, and supporting low-income families through affordable childcare. What do you feel are the greatest needs in this community?\""]}, {"topic": "Nonprofit", "question": "Many nonprofits take an apologetic approach when asking for funding. What is your fundraising approach?", "answers": ["Assure the interviewer that you are comfortable when it comes to asking for funds. How would you describe your approach to asking for donations?", "\"My approach to fundraising is simple. I ask for donations assuming that they are going to say yes. I have approximately five years in corporate fundraising with targets at $4M per year. I am very confident in my ability to fund-raise in a simple and non-apologetic way.\"", "\"My approach is \"You don't know until you ask.\" I am unafraid of receiving a 'no' because for every few no's, there is a yes waiting!\""]}, {"topic": "Nonprofit", "question": "Do you have experience with writing grant proposals?", "answers": ["Grant funding is a vital part of many nonprofit organizations. If you have exposure to this type of work, walk the interviewer through some of your grant writing success. If you do not have experience with it, discuss how you could assist and learn.", "\"I fully understand the importance of grant proposals as it accounts for millions of dollars awarded every year to a variety of causes. I am a solid writer; however, my current organization employs professional writers to do these tasks. I have assisted in the way of collecting data for our fundraising plans.\"", "\"Yes, I have written approximately five grants in my career so far. They are tedious and challenging, but in a way that I enjoy. Will grant writing be a part of this role?\""]}, {"topic": "Nonprofit", "question": "Tell me about a contribution you made to the last team you worked on.", "answers": ["It is essential to show the interviewer that you are a team player. Talk about a time that you were recently expected to achieve a goal in a team setting. How did you go over and above to ensure that your contribution was felt?", "\"My biggest contribution to my last team came in the form of leadership. I am a natural leader and can foster strong communication with my team which directly impacted the overall results.\"", "\"My most notable contribution was my ability to analyze and predict market trends, and then create a successful marketing strategy.  Before me, there was no one with a true marketing background on the team.\""]}, {"topic": "Nonprofit", "question": "Give me an example of a time when you went above and beyond.", "answers": ["Display to the interviewer that you can do more than the bare minimum. Show that you can react appropriately when you see that your employer has a need that goes beyond your usual day-to-day expectations.", "\"Last week I noticed that my manager had not completed the schedule for the following week. Some of the staff were complaining that they didn't have their work schedule yet. Rather than going to my manager with the complaint, I offered to take on some of her workload so that she would have the time to complete the schedule. We worked together for a couple of overtime hours that day and were able to catch her up on everything. It felt good to help but also benefited me by way of organization.\"", "\"I often go above and beyond what is expected of me. Most recently, I agreed to cover for a co-worker who was on short-term medical leave. I worked 10 hour days for two weeks so that our work did not suffer any setbacks.\""]}, {"topic": "Nonprofit", "question": "What are your salary expectations?", "answers": ["The best way to discuss your salary expectations is to use your current earnings as an example. Be open, and honest. Transparency is the best choice when salary based questions arise.", "\"Currently, I earn a base salary of $45,000 per year plus a potential 20% annual bonus. Last year my earnings were $52,000, and I would like to stay in the same range or slightly higher.\"", "\"I am currently making $60,000 per year with two bonus opportunities.  I am looking for compensation that is aligned with the role and provides an opportunity for growth.\""]}, {"topic": "Nonprofit", "question": "Do you feel performance should be rewarded over experience?", "answers": ["Do you feel that you should be paid based on tenure, or results? Discuss this with the interviewer and back your answer with an example, if possible.", "\"I feel that employees should be paid, and rewarded, based on their performance. A new employee would be greatly motivated through being rewarded for performance, and it encourages a healthy competition with tenured employees.\"", "\"I feel both performance and experience should be equally rewarded and weighted.\""]}, {"topic": "Nonprofit", "question": "Rate your communication skills from 1-10 with proper examples backing your given rating.", "answers": ["On a scale of 1-10, how skilled are you in communication? Why did you choose that particular rating for yourself?", "\"I rate my communication skills as a 9/10 as I will, on occasion, have times when I am not as clear as I would like to be. My supervisor and co-workers will attest to my clear and concise communication skills. Because I am an open leader, my team will let me know if I need to clarify anything.\"", "\"I will rate myself an 8.5 because I consider myself a strong communicator.  It is the foundation of all success in business.  I am always striving to be a better communicator, so I leave the rest of the scale as an aspirational measure.\""]}, {"topic": "Nonprofit", "question": "How do you like to encourage ideas in others?", "answers": ["Encouragement to others is a great skill to possess. Talk to the interviewer about your ability to encourage creative ideas in your team members.", "\"I like to encourage other people to be creative in their thinking and present ideas to the company, no matter how off the wall they may seem. Some of our most successful employees are ones who are confident in their ability to bring forward their unique ideas. I encourage participation through an open door policy and strong praise for those who show initiative.\"", "\"I encourage people to tap into the best parts of themselves. It helps to ask probing questions to get them to generate ideas on their own. I have found that by painting a long-term vision for where I want to go, my team will often jump in with creative solutions to get us there.\""]}, {"topic": "Nonprofit", "question": "When have you used an inventive method to stretch company resources beyond the normal level?", "answers": ["If you have an expense account or resource allowance, it is very respectful to the company to be as thoughtful with that allowance as possible. Talk to the interviewer about a time when you have been able to stretch company resources.", "\"I have recently implemented a schedule that allows for ride-sharing rewards which have cut down on our company's fuel expense by $9000 per month. I am quite proud of this initiative because it is not only financially responsible but also environmentally friendly.\"", "\"This is a practice I often utilize to maximize company resources and optimize value to the clients. I recycle a lot of company materials to make the most of our resources. I also do this with people regarding cross training and sharing understanding across departments.\""]}, {"topic": "Nonprofit", "question": "When have you shown great integrity at work?", "answers": ["Integrity is best displayed through honesty and consistent moral values. Talk to the interviewer about the way (s) that you show your integrity in the workplace.", "\"In my last position, I was responsible for the cash deposit on a daily basis. There was never a discrepancy, in the four years that I worked there. I best show my integrity by being a consistently reliable employee.\"", "\"I show integrity every day at work by being my true self. The \"me\" that you see at work is the \"me\" that my family and friends get. I am an honest and genuine person.\""]}, {"topic": "Nonprofit", "question": "On a scale from 1 to 10, how honest are you?", "answers": ["Do you feel that you are a sincere person or do you have room for growth? This question could be a tricky one as nobody is always 100% honest. Answer to the best of your ability and back your reply by speaking about your ethics.", "\"I would love to give myself a 10/10 for honesty but truthfully - nobody is 100% honest all of the time. I will give myself an nine because I always do my best to be as honest as possible.\"", "\"I put a heavy focus on honesty and trustworthiness in the workplace, as well as in my personal life.  Because I strive for complete honesty, I will rate myself as a 10/10. My values are solid.\""]}, {"topic": "Nonprofit", "question": "Have you ever been advised by a fellow employee or supervisor to lie about a situation? How did you handle this ethical dilemma?", "answers": ["Ethical dilemmas in the workplace will come up from time to time. Assure the interviewer that you can handle these types of difficulties with professionalism and poise.", "\"I have never been told to lie to a fellow employee or supervisor on the job. If I were to be asked to lie, I absolutely would not do that. I am not the type of personality to be pushed around on the job. I will always be myself and keep my integrity first.\"", "\"I have never been advised to lie in a situation and would not tolerate being put in such an ethical dilemma.\""]}, {"topic": "Nonprofit", "question": "Are you applying for any other jobs?", "answers": ["It always puts a little bit of fire under the hiring manager if they are aware that you are actively looking for a new position. Tell the interviewer about your search so far.", "\"I am keeping an eye out for viable positions. Although I am not in final stages with any other company, I am actively seeking a new position.\"", "\"I am looking for a job that will provide me as much value as I am looking to contribute to an organization, so yes, I am in the process of exploring opportunities at companies that appeal to me.\""]}, {"topic": "Public+Works", "question": "Why would you rather work in the public works sector versus the private sector?", "answers": ["There is a significant difference between public works and working in the private sector. Public works often offer better pay. There is generally more job security, excellent benefits, and other perks such as a pension. However, the private sector may offer faster growth, better tech, and other perks. Discuss with the interviewer why you are choosing to find a role in the public sector versus private.", "\"Each sector, private or public, come with their challenges; however, I feel that the offering from the public works sector better fits my needs. There is more job security, and opportunities for competitive benefits and pension; all factors that I consider as I raise and support my family.\"", "\"I have spent time comparing public and private sector work, as I want to begin my career on the right foot. A recent Fraser Institute report showed me that public works jobs pay more, on average, but also offer more job security in unionized and non-unionized roles. Starting my career, it's important to me that I build a secure future for myself. For those reasons, public sector work became the clear choice.\""]}, {"topic": "Public+Works", "question": "At Company ABC we do everything as a team. Have you ever had difficulty working in a team environment?", "answers": ["The ability to work in a team environment is a critical skill to Company ABC. The interviewer needs to make sure that your approach to work will complement their existing employees and aligns well with their promise to the public; whom they serve. Safety and efficiency are achieved through great teamwork so you must show the interviewer that you can work positively in a team setting.", "\"My current team is incredible. We collaborate very well and achieve this great teamwork through clear and consistent communication efforts. I have not had troubles in any previous team environment, and look forward to experiencing even more collaboration with the teams here at Company ABC.\"", "\"I have no difficulty in team-based environments. That is where I thrive, as a highly collaborative crew member. I can work well on my own as well, but I do prefer the variety and excitement that comes with teamwork.\""]}, {"topic": "Public+Works", "question": "Talk to me about your safety-related training and your overall safety record in your current job.", "answers": ["Company ABC must put the safety of the public, and their employees before anything else. For this reason, they are careful to hire people who are just as safety-focused. If you have safety-related training, take the time to walk the interviewer through this education. For instance, maybe you have some safety-related tickets or certifications that will solidify your expertise in safety. Talk about the safety precautions that you take on the job, or plan to take in this role.", "\"Safety must be at the forefront of everything that I do in this industry. Over the past six years, I have taken safety certifications such as Heights Safety, Electrical Safety, Chemical Safety, and Road Safety. I brought these certifications for you, in case you would like a copy for my candidate file. I have never had an accident in the workplace, and I believe this is due to my attention to detail, willingness to pace myself, and strong communication during projects.\"", "\"The Company ABC job posting mentioned a variety of potential hazards which included confined spaces, frequent lifting, heavy equipment, traffic, extreme weather, and chemical exposure. I understand the importance of exercising safety in all that I do when facing these types of situations. I am new to my career, so I have not received any formal safety training; however, I am eager to learn and am willing to begin studying in preparation for this role.\""]}, {"topic": "Public+Works", "question": "Stress is a natural occurrence in the public works industry. How do you react in the most stressful situations?", "answers": ["The interviewer needs to know that you can deal with the stress that may come in this role. Because Company ABC is responsible for critical public services, the stakes can be high. Your ability to manage stress professionally and productively can make all the difference when a critical situation arises. Think back to a time when you had to deal with a significant stressor at work. Walk the interviewer through your reaction, the action that you took, and the positive outcome in the end.", "\"I understand that situations can unravel quickly when dealing with critical public services. Our community has high expectations for this department, so I must manage those expectations with poise. In my current role, there is a great amount of pressure to meet very tight project deadlines. These projects have many moving parts and demanding stakeholders, which is enough to make a lot of people quit their jobs. I am resilient and have stayed with my company much longer than the average tenure.\"", "\"I handle stress very well, and my references will wholeheartedly agree when you call them. I am able to remain focused and on deadline, because I ask questions, request help when needed, and keep open lines of communication at all stages of a project.\""]}, {"topic": "Public+Works", "question": "Company ABC hires only the most reliable team members. How often were you unexpectedly absent or late from work in your previous position?", "answers": ["Each role and public works provider is different; however, Company ABC may have a variety of shifts that involves on-call work. Teams may be small, meaning that your contribution and level of reliability is critical to their success. Talk about how reliable you are in your current role, leaning on a specific example of a time you came through for your team, or what your references say about you.", "\"In my career, I am proud to have had zero unexcused absences. My supervisor often comments on how reliable I am, and that I am an excellent example to my team. I have around three weeks of vacation time, which I take when it is seasonally convenient for my employer. I am always ten minutes early for work, and am often available to cover shifts when needed.\"", "\"The last sick day I took was last year and came with a doctors' note. I am not fickle when it comes to showing up for my team and my employer. When you call my references, they will attest to the fact that I am reliable and a strong team player.\""]}, {"topic": "Public+Works", "question": "Company ABC seeks trades professionals with a variety of skills. Name for me your top three skills.", "answers": ["It's hard for most people to brag about themselves in an interview; however, questions like this require just that from you! Think back to any consistent compliments you receive from your coworkers or your boss. What are you most often endorsed for on LinkedIn? What are you most frequently asked about when it comes to your career expertise? If you are having difficulty carving out which skills are your top skills, as yourself these questions and begin to create a list. Once you are sure of your top three talents, then be prepared to discuss how these skills will benefit Company ABC, should you be hired.", "\"My biggest strengths include my mechanical knowledge, my troubleshooting skills, and my willingness to work overtime or fill in for others when needed. These skills make me a competitive candidate for Company ABC. I can adapt well in most situations and will need little training when it comes to the equipment used in this role.\"", "\"Looking at the job posting by Company ABC I believe that my top skills, which will benefit you the most, including my clean driving record and confidence behind the wheel. Also, my understanding of the tools and machinery used in this job will be of great value. This knowledge includes a strong understanding of equipment (A), (B). and (C).\""]}, {"topic": "Public+Works", "question": "Company ABC employs a diverse range of trades and administration personnel. How do you feel about working in a highly diverse environment?", "answers": ["As an employee in the public works industry, you will find diversity in every team and community that you serve. It's diversity that makes innovation and positive change a possibility! Company ABC wants to know how you feel about working in an inclusive environment and how you go about embracing diversity. Diversity can include genders, religious backgrounds, sexual orientation, special abilities, and more.", "\"I truly admire the effort that Company ABC makes when it comes to diversity and inclusion in the workplace. I enjoy learning from those different from me and am thrilled to be exposed to new relationships and experiences. Everyone walks a unique path, and I celebrate that.\"", "\"I am a minority, so I understand first-hand the importance of a highly diverse work environment. I am sensitive to others, and their unique circumstances so I do appreciate that Company ABC puts in a dedicated effort to do the same.\""]}, {"topic": "Public+Works", "question": "How do you feel about working in a union environment?", "answers": ["Some public works roles are union based, where others are not. Despite some unions having a bad reputation, there are many positive factors for working in a unionized environment. These include fair pay and job security. If this role with Company ABC requires you to be part of a union, discuss your willingness to join the union. Be sure to ask insightful questions about their collective agreement.", "\"I currently work in a unionized job and have for the past eight years. The union approach is not new to me, and I have enjoyed the benefits thus far. My current union works hard to ensure that employees are safe and treated fairly. I look forward to learning more about your union and collective agreement.\"", "\"I am not overly familiar with union environments, but I do understand that this role is union based. Could you take some time to share with me how the union would impact my employment experience at Company ABC?\""]}, {"topic": "Public+Works", "question": "Public services never stop running. Are you willing to work a double shift, weekends, evenings, overtime, and holidays?", "answers": ["Depending on the role, and whether or not this position is unionized, you may be asked to work overtime, doubles, evenings, weekends, and more. Before you blindly agree to work any hours, make sure you are clear on expectations. \nIf you cannot meet the schedule expectations at Company ABC try discussing precisely what you can offer. There may be some room to agree on a revised schedule.", "\"I am available to work all seven days of the week; however, due to family commitments, these hours must be during that day. With notice, I can work overtime and the odd weekend when needed. Will my availability meet the needs of Company ABC?\"", "\"Being new to my career, I believe it's important that I offer flexibility in my schedule. I wish to grow my career as quickly as possible with Company ABC and part of that means being available and willing to work the hours offered to me. I will do everything I can to be flexible and accommodating.\""]}, {"topic": "Public+Works", "question": "What would happen in the absence of public services? Do you understand why this job with Company ABC is so critical?", "answers": ["Public services are critical to the good of the community. Public works ensure that communities and their citizens receive access to basic human needs, at an affordable price. Public works are responsible for providing clean, safe, and maintained parks for children. They cover necessities such as clean drinking water and affordable access to reliable public transit. \n\nThe interviewer at Company ABC wants to see that you understand why their purpose is vital to the community. Share what you know, being sure to express your understanding of the scope of their work and responsibilities.", "\"Without Company ABC and the public services that you provide, our communities would not be safe and certainly would not be as happy. Our community thrives in part because of the work done by Company ABC. I will take utmost responsibility in this role, and will act as a public servant every day on the job.\"", "\"In the absence of public works, our community and its citizens would not be able to enjoy clean parks, treated water, consistent electricity, safe roads, and reliable public transit. Public works are all-encompassing and critical to the well-being and happiness of the public. I completely understand the important role that Company ABC plays in all of this and am eager to contribute.\""]}, {"topic": "Public+Works", "question": "List for me some of the main duties in your current role that will apply to this role with Company ABC.", "answers": ["The hiring authority would like to see the parallel between the duties of their job and the role that you currently hold. Your answer could include a mix of hard and soft skills that you believe are transferable to this position with Company ABC. These skills could consist of specialized equipment or machinery that you operate. Skills could include team leadership, scheduling, hiring, and project management. The primary purpose of this question is for the interviewer to be able to picture you in this role with Company ABC easily.", "\"The job posting at Company ABC piqued my interest since many of the role responsibilities aligned with my current job including (A), (B), and (C). These duties, in particular, are ones that I perform daily. I also bring experience leading a team of 15 trades professionals, creating their schedules, and delivering quarterly performance reports.\"", "\"As a recent graduate, the most important transferrable skills that I bring to Company ABC include my ability to work cohesively on group projects, meet deadlines, and communicate with clarity both verbally and written.\""]}, {"topic": "Public+Works", "question": "What does hard work mean to you?", "answers": ["Everyone interprets hard work differently, and the hiring authority at Company ABC wants to know what it means to you! Hard work can mean doing what is expected of you, even when you don't feel like it. Working hard can mean delivering more than expected without being asked. Show the interviewer that you are not a 'bare minimum' type of employee and that you are prepared to give your best in this role.", "\"I was raised to be a hard worker, and had excellent examples in both of my parents. To work hard means to strive to deliver your absolute best every day. It means to overdeliver on what you are asked to do, all while maintaining a positive attitude. I will contribute greatly to the goals of Company ABC with my great outlook and ability to work hard.\"", "\"Being a hard worker means that you take the time to understand the goals of your employer, and you become invested in those goals. It means staying until the job is done and done well. One way that I show my work ethic is to continually keep an open mind regarding potential improvements in my work, or ways to optimize efficiency on the job.\""]}, {"topic": "Public+Works", "question": "Have you overseen the work of someone else, in any of your previous positions? How do you feel about being a team leader?", "answers": ["The interviewer would like to know how you feel about future leadership opportunities. Think about a time when you have led someone else, or a group of people, at work or in your personal life. If you are newer to your career, perhaps you led a group project in school or led a volunteer effort. Show the interviewer how you strive to be an excellent example to others.", "\"Yes, I have overseen a team of 5 others in the past. I enjoy being a leader in situations where I know my job very well and am confident that I can guide others with ease. For me, leadership does not always equate to management. If I am not in an official leadership role, I am still able to be a great example to others through a strong work ethic and a positive mindset.\"", "\"I always strive to be a positive example to others, even when I am not in a formal leadership position. While attending university, I enjoyed being the encourager in group projects, and I also volunteered as a tutor. If hired at Company ABC I would take every opportunity to be a good example, whether in a team lead function or not.\""]}, {"topic": "Public+Works", "question": "This position aside, which Company ABC department would you work with if you were given the opportunity?", "answers": ["In public works, there are a variety of areas in which you can work, including public recreational areas such as parks and green spaces. Public works can also include the care of community centers and government-owned building. Transport infrastructure and roads are often considered public works as well. In addition to these, public services such as water supply, sewage treatment, and electrical grids fall under the umbrella of the public works. The interviewer would like to know, aside from the role to which you have applied, what other areas of public works catch your attention. Discuss any other interests that you have.", "\"I have a variety of interests and, aside from this position, would be happy to learn more about water supply and treatment. I believe that water supply is one of the most important services we can provide to the public. It's important to me that I understand how water treatment processes work.\"", "\"Although my primary interest is in the landscaping and beautification of public spaces such as parks and green spaces, I do have an interest in roads and infrastructure. If there were an opportunity to learn about other public works services at Company ABC I would choose roads and bridges. It's fascinating to me how the city comes to decisions on road expansions and more.\""]}, {"topic": "Public+Works", "question": "This role requires a great deal of physical stamina. Are you able to meet this requirement?", "answers": ["Your ability to meet the physical needs of this role will be essential to Company ABC. There is no need to overcomplicate this response. Working in public works, depending on the department and your official position might be very physically demanding. Assure the interviewer that you can meet these demands without hurting yourself or others. If you currently work in a job that is demanding on you, physically, be sure to share those details!", "\"Before applying to Company ABC I carefully read through the physical requirements of the job. I am confident that I can meet these needs while delivering upon your commitment to a safe work environment for all.\"", "\"I like to keep fit and have no hesitations when it comes to the physical requirements of this role. I can lift 55 pounds regularly, stand, bend, and walk most of the day.\""]}, {"topic": "Public+Works", "question": "What does delivering a public service mean to you?", "answers": ["Company ABC is looking for alignment between their core mission, and what you hope to accomplish in this role. Be prepared to discuss what it means to work in a public service sector. Think of this as an opportunity to give your own mini-mission statement.", "\"For me, delivering a public service means that I work hard to make the lives of those in my community better. I do my best to create improvements for those that use public services, ensuring that our community receives uninterrupted service when it matters the most.\"", "\"Delivering a public service means being consistent and engaged when it comes to delivering various service-related needs to my community. As a public works employee, I aim to do my best every day so that everyone in my community can enjoy the way of life that they expect and deserve.\""]}, {"topic": "Public+Works", "question": "There are a vast amount of growth opportunities within Company ABC. Where would you like your career in public works to take you?", "answers": ["Before your interview, you should have an excellent idea of the types of growth and opportunities available to you in the years to come. If you were to advance your career, what are the next natural steps to take? How have the people before you progressed with Company ABC? \n\nYou can find this information by researching on the Company ABC website or even checking out the LinkedIn profiles of the professionals who came before you; taking note of their career progression. Talk to the hiring authority about future goals and opportunity.", "\"I did some research on the Company ABC website and see that you offer endless opportunities for growth through a variety of departments. I want to work my way into a team leadership or management role with Company ABC in the next two years. I have some valuable leadership training that I look forward to utilizing.\"", "\"One of the benefits of being employed in the public works sector is job security and opportunity for growth. I would like to see my career advance to include crew management opportunities. I like to train others, teaching them what I know, so any leadership opportunity that includes training new hires would be an exciting advancement for me.\""]}, {"topic": "Public+Works", "question": "Are you familiar with the American Public Works Association? Would you consider gaining accreditation or certification from your nearest chapter?", "answers": ["The American Public Works Association (APWA) is one of the largest networks and organizations service public works professionals in North America. They boast over 30,000 members who benefit significantly from their resources. The APWA is a non-profit organization that focuses' primarily on educating public works employees, helping them to grow in their careers. Discuss what you know about the APWA. \n\nIf you are a member of the APWA or a similar group, be ready to discuss how this organization has positively impacted your career. If you are not a member of any professional associations related to public works, be sure to express your interest in learning more and becoming well connected in your industry.", "\"I am not a member of the APWA; however, there is a similar association called XYZ.  I have had the opportunity to take some coursework through this non-profit group on topics such as Public Infrastructure and Project Management. It has been a valuable experience for me, and I have grown my network exponentially since joining.\"", "\"I have heard of the APWA and understand that they are a non-profit organization focused on educating and connecting public works professionals. I look forward to being eligible for membership and growing my knowledge and network.\""]}, {"topic": "Public+Works", "question": "In your opinion, what defines 'Public Works'?", "answers": ["'Public works' is a broad term that refers to many government services and structures. Public works are provided by the government, to the community, to provide essential services and a better quality of life to those living in the region. Briefly explain what the term 'public works' means to you; showing the interviewer that you understand the industry.", "\"I understand public works to be a broad term for services provided to the public, paid for by the government. Public works can be roads, water, electricity, infrastructure, parks, and more.\"", "\"To me, 'public works' is a catch-all term for services and structures provided to communities by the government. Parks and green spaces are part of public works; as are roads and public transit systems. Also included in public works could be electrical grids and water treatment facilities.\""]}, {"topic": "Public+Works", "question": "Do you have experience working around and operating heavy equipment?", "answers": ["It's crucial to Company ABC that you can safely and effectively use the equipment required on the job. Rather than giving an exhaustive list of the type of equipment you have used, try a more conversational approach. Discuss the heavy equipment training you have received and any particular areas of expertise. \n\nIf you are new to working around heavy equipment, show that you are eager to learn. You can ask questions about the type of equipment you'll be using. You can also ask if there are available resources for you to learn more before your start date.", "\"In my current role, I operate heavy equipment around 30% of the day. The equipment I am best versed in includes (A), and (B); which align with the equipment mentioned in the Company ABC job posting. I have a strong mechanical background, which also allows me to troubleshoot and repair minor issues on the job site.\"", "\"I have worked around heavy equipment; however, operating the equipment would be a new skill for me. I am mechanically savvy and understand the main components of most of the equipment used in this role.\""]}, {"topic": "Public+Works", "question": "Your background is not in public works. What qualifies you for this position?", "answers": ["Coming from the public works industry may not be a requirement for this role. In fact, with the right transferrable skills, it's straightforward for a qualified candidate like yourself to make a successful industry change. Be prepared to talk about the transferable skills you bring to this position. These transferable skills could be heavy equipment operation, team leadership, safety training, customer service experience, or technical capabilities. Make your case as to why you are the top candidate, regardless of your direct industry experience.", "\"The public works industry is something that I can learn. I have performed a great deal of research on Company ABC and know that I would be a fit in many ways. For instance, I can manage a crew, schedule multiple crew members over a variety of projects, conduct safety training, and report to a variety of stakeholders. I am highly qualified for this role and look forward to showing you how I can make a positive impact here.\"", "\"I come from the private sector, specifically in energy; however, the importance of what I did in terms of accuracy and safety are the same as the expectations with Company ABC. I put safety first, and I am highly technical and mechanically minded. These skills will come with me, no matter the industry in which I work.\""]}, {"topic": "Public+Works", "question": "Tell me about one area you could improve on, and one area where you are strongest.", "answers": ["This question is a smart, blended way of asking about your greatest strength and your greatest weakness. Think back to any performance reviews, or verbal and written feedback from your current supervisor. If you have formal performance reviews, what did you discuss? If you do not have formal performance reviews, mention any input that you consistently receive; both positive and constructive. \n\nWhen discussing your weakness, or area for improvement, avoid topics that would ruin your chances of landing the job. For instance, if you are interviewing for a landscaping role, you should not say that you are uncomfortable operating machinery. When it comes to your area for improvement, discuss what you are actively doing to improve.", "\"My manager loves that I am independent and can figure out challenging problems quickly. With that said, I do know that I should work on my patience when it comes to training new hires. Because I work fast sometimes, that means reminding myself to slow down and meet other people where they are. When working with a new hire, I let them know that I work fast and to ask me to slow down or repeat a section of training anytime they need. It's important to me that I create a comfortable learning atmosphere for everyone.\"", "\"My supervisor is delighted with my technical skills and my ability to solve problems through reverse engineering. One area for improvement is to improve my documentation. I document; however, sometimes not to the detail and level that my manager would like to see. To improve on this, I created a framework to follow for each situation. This framework includes information such as the situation, the action I took, and the result.\""]}, {"topic": "Public+Works", "question": "Safety is everything to us at Company ABC. How do you embrace a culture of safety?", "answers": ["Safety is incredibly important in any job and even more so when working within the government and public works. Take some time to learn about the safety goals, and safety record of Company ABC. You may be able to find information on their website or through an online search. How do the values of Company ABC match your approach to safety in the workplace?", "\"Serving the public and providing comfort and safety is a running theme at Company ABC. You help our communities thrive through public services such as (A), (B), and (C). To contribute to your culture of safety, I will learn how to use all equipment given to me properly, and I will learn protocols and processes; following them to a tee.\"", "\"From my research, I see that Company ABC puts many safety precautions into place, but you also understand that safety comes from proper employee development and operational standards. To embrace your culture of safety, I will take every opportunity to learn, develop, and grow, ensuring that I abide by your policies and lead by example.\""]}, {"topic": "Public+Works", "question": "Company ABC works on multiple projects at a time. Are you accustomed to multi-tasking and prioritizing your work?", "answers": ["Multi-tasking and prioritizing multiple projects is an essential skill in the busy public works industry where you will have many tasks on the go at one time. Assure the interviewer that you are capable of handling a variety of tasks and deadlines at one time. Talk about your current role and how multi-tasking is an expectation. You could tell a story about how you delivered on multiple expectations in tandem. If you are new to your career, you can draw from your post-secondary experience, volunteer work, or even a team sports.", "\"In my current position I juggle multiple tasks at one time, with a variety of stakeholders. I also answer to two supervisors in two different departments. This experience has helped me to develop great multi-tasking skills, which I am eager to apply in this role with Company ABC.\"", "\"Multi-tasking is a skill that I continue to improve. I tend to concentrate hard on my tasks at hand, and am working to improve on my ability to be pulled away to multiple projects. I did well during university when I had multiple projects due in one week, along with a variety of exams.\""]}, {"topic": "Public+Works", "question": "Do you have experience with emergency management and response?", "answers": ["Many public works services help communities to protect themselves from emergencies, disasters, and hazards. The interviewer would like to know if you have any experience working in an environment where you may need to react quickly in critical situations. Show the interviewer that you are capable of handling the stress levels and clear thinking that comes with emergency management and response.", "\"In my previous role, I worked in water treatment and did come across a variety of mission-critical situations including contamination and flooding. I am confident in my ability to react quickly and appropriately in emergencies.\"", "\"I work quickly and can think on my feet; giving me the ability to react professionally in any situation, including an emergency. I have taken coursework on safety and accident prevention, which will help me as I learn more about emergency preparedness, response, and recovery.\""]}, {"topic": "Public+Works", "question": "Please share with me your salary expectations.", "answers": ["It is essential to be able to discuss salary in an interview openly. For many public works jobs, the per hour or salary range is listed in the job posting. If you are currently working, use your current earnings as a benchmark. If you are new to your career and are unsure what to ask for, try out a free online salary calculator. You want to give the interviewer a clear idea of what you would like to earn, assuring them that your needs fall into what they are offering.", "\"I would like to be transparent about expectations, so I will share that I am currently making $22/hour plus health benefits and two weeks' vacation time. I want my next opportunity to reflect my recently completed leadership coursework and aim to earn in the $24-26 per hour range plus three weeks' vacation time. Does this fit within the offering here at Company ABC?\"", "\"I would like to earn slightly above where I am now. Currently, I earn $25/hour plus overtime and an opportunity for a quarterly bonus. My target income for the coming year is $60,000.\""]}, {"topic": "Public+Works", "question": "Tell me about your least favorite job. Why did you dislike this job?", "answers": ["It is pretty common to have had a job in the past that we don't particularly like. What sets you apart is how you react in this type of situation. Briefly break down for the interviewer what made the job unpleasant, but spend more of your time discussing what you did to make it more enjoyable. The hiring authority at Company ABC wants to see that you are proactive in improving your situation versus spending your time complaining.", "\"My least favorite job was a clerical position that I took right out of high school. There was a great deal of data entry, and it was very repetitive. I am social and creative, so this position became tiresome very quickly. I decided to learn what I could during my time there. I took the opportunity to learn more about accounting, balancing books, and using more advanced parts of Excel.\"", "\"During my college days, I worked nights in a warehouse. The money was good, but the work was a grind! I was timed for productivity and could not even stop the clock for a washroom break. It felt like a sweatshop environment, but I stuck through it because I was determined to pay off my student loans. The great news is that I made some good connections and was able to find employment in another part of the warehouse immediately after graduation.\""]}, {"topic": "Public+Works", "question": "In your last performance review, what was one suggested area of improvement?", "answers": ["This question is another way of asking about your weaknesses. Give the interviewer a brief take on your most recent performance review, touching on what you do very well and what you were asked to improve. Show that you can take constructive feedback and implement it willingly. If you do not receive formal performance reviews, you can rely on a conversation or meeting that you have had at work where there was a similar discussion.", "\"My current boss recently mentioned that I could strengthen my level of comfortability with heavy machinery. I immediately enrolled myself in some classes at our local trades school to boost my performance in this area.\"", "\"In my last performance meeting, my boss asked that I start working on becoming more comfortable with speaking in front of groups. He wants me to train our new hires one day on safety and other protocols. To meet this need, I have joined toastmasters and attend meetings once a week. I can already feel an improvement in the area of public speaking.\""]}, {"topic": "Public+Works", "question": "Rank your communication skills from 1-10. Please justify your ranking.", "answers": ["Ranking your communication skills from 1-10 is a quick way for the interviewer to gauge how positively you see yourself when it comes to communicating in the workplace. Nobody is a perfect communicator, so avoid ranking yourself a 10/10; however, be careful not to undercut yourself either. Provide an example of when you improved communication in the workplace.", "\"There is always more for me to learn; however, I value clear communication. For that reason, I rank myself an 8 out of 10. I ensure that my coworkers understand the goals for the day, and I am in communication with my supervisor throughout the day. My boss is always aware of what we have planned for the day, and the week.\"", "\"I rank my communication skills as a 7.5 out of 10. I have much to learn but am always striving to do my best. Clear messaging, whether it be verbal or written, is imperative to a successful operation. I take the time to ensure my emails contain all the information needed before I send. When speaking in person, I ask if I do not understand. I never hesitate to gain clarification.\""]}, {"topic": "Public+Works", "question": "How would you handle conflict within your team?", "answers": ["Conflict can happen when you employ teams of individuals with different goals, communication styles, and backgrounds. The important part is that any dispute is swiftly resolved and does not cause damage to Company ABC or the people it serves. \n\nThink of a time where you experienced some conflict amongst your team. Perhaps there was a disagreement regarding shifts, priorities, or the way to approach a project. Show the interviewer that you are mature and able to remain professional in situations like this.", "\"I believe that dealing with conflict can be a normal part of work; however, the conflict needs to be dealt with openly and quickly. Conflict, when handled the right way, can bring a team even closer together. Recently, my team did not agree on the approach to take regarding the prioritization of three landscaping projects. We all sat down and gave our opinions. After listening to each other, we collectively decided which action to take. I allow my team to disagree; however, I ask for professionalism at the same time.\"", "\"I recently had a coworker angry with me because I would not cover their evening shift. Normally I am a team player; however, it was my mothers' birthday dinner, and I could not miss the event. After two days of this teammate giving me the cold shoulder, I approached them head-on. I reminded them that I was willing to be helpful; however, not when communication was lacking and not when I felt disrespected. The coworker apologized, and we quickly moved on from the situation.\""]}]